High seas. Deep terror. Try to stay calm.
Dead Calm is a thriller, horror film directed by Phillip Noyce.
An Australian couple takes a sailing trip in the Pacific
to get over the recent loss of their son.
While on the open sea, they come across a sinking ship with
one survivor who is not at all what he seems.
Rae Ingram, played by Nicole Kidman.
John Ingram, played by Sam Neill.
Hughie Warriner, played by Billy Zane.
Doctor, played by George Shevtsov.
Russell Bellows, played by Rod Mullinar.
Danny, played by Joshua Tilden.
Dead Calm is a 1989 Australian psychological thriller film directed by Phillip Noyce,
produced by George Miller, and starring Sam Neill, Nicole Kidman and Billy Zane.
The screenplay by Terry Hayes was based on the 1963
novel of the same name by Charles Williams.
Filmed around the Great Barrier Reef, the plot focuses on a married couple, who, after tragically losing their son, are
spending some time isolated at sea, when they come across a stranger who has abandoned a sinking ship.
Notably, the movie is the first successful film adaptation of the novel, after Orson Welles worked for a number of years to
complete his own film based on it titled The Deep, though it ultimately went unreleased and uncompleted.
Dead Calm was generally well received, with critics praising Neill,
Kidman, and Zane's performances and the oceanic cinematography.
It was nominated in eight categories at the 1989 Australian Film
Institute Awards, including Best Film, and won four.
Modern retrospective analyses have been favorable, with The New York
Times naming it one of the 1000 best films ever made.
The film explores themes of australia, sense of guilt,
toxication, loss of loved one, shipwreck.
The tone is dark and intense.